Finding Aid for the Japanese American Research Project Collection about Japanese in the U.S. (Yuji Ichioka papers) LSC.2010.00
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Materials regarding Incarceration Camps and World War II
  - Materials regarding Wartime Incarceration
    - Senji Shyjo [characters] Incarceration Camp Publications, 4.0 linear ft.
      - Santa Fe detention facility, New Mexico., July 1943-February 1944 (Box 332)
        - Santa Fe Jihsha [characters]. Santa Fe Nihonjin Shyjo Jimmeiroku [characters] [Roster of Japanese incarcerees in the Santa Fe Internment Center]. Santa Fe., 1943; (Mimeographed, 50 pp.) (Box 332)
        - Santa Fe Kirisuto Kykai [characters]. Kaiin Kyy Meibo [characters] [Roster of the members and friends of the Santa Fe Christian Church]. Santa Fe., 1943; (Mimeographed, 20 pp.) (Box 332)
      - Crystal City detention facility, Texas., July 1943-April 1946 (Box 333)
        - Crystal City Times. Weekly., November 13-27, 1944; January 2, 1946; August 13, 1945; January 21, 1946; (6 issues) (Box 333)
          vol.1, no.4-6 (November 13-27, 1944)
          vol.2, no.32 (August 13, 1945)
          vol.3, no.1 (January 2, 1946)
          vol.3, no.3 (January 21, 1946)
        - Homu [characters] [The Home]. Crystal City. Irregular publication., May 20, 1945; July 12 & 25, August 2 & 8, 1945; (Mimeographed, 5 items) (Box 333)
          no.6 (May 20, 1945)
          no.11-14 (July 12 & 25, August 2 & 8, 1945)
        - Jichikai Jih [characters] [Jichikai Times]. Crystal City. Daily., July 1943-April 1946; (Mimeographed) (Box 333)
          no.1-6 (July 9-August 10, 1943)
          no.8-24 (August 24-October 18, 1943)
          no.16-18 (November 1-15, 1943)
          no.21-23 (November 8-28, 1943)
          no.24-41 (January 18-June 12, 1944)
          no.44-63 (July 11-November 2, 1944)
          no.65-112 (November 4-December 30, 1944)
          no.113-324 (January 3-September 7, 1945)
          no.329-337 (September 17-October 5, 1945)
          no.329-337 (November 23-December 31, 1945)
          no.382-401 (January 2-25, 2946)
          Nos.404-445 (January 30-March 28, 1946)
          and Nos. 447-445 (April 1-11, 1946)
        - Kirisuto Kykai Shh [characters] [Crystal City Japanese Christian Church Weekly Bulletin]. Crystal City. Weekly., (Mimeographed) (Box 333)
        - Los Andes. Nos. 3-5, 40. Crystal City., November 13-27, 1944; August 13, 1945; (3 issues) (Box 333)
          A weekly publication by the Peruvian Japanese who were incarcerated in the Crystal City detention facility.
        - Yehudi Express. Volume 1, no.10. Crystal City. Semi-quarterly., March 21, 1946; (Mimeographed) (Box 333)
          An English publication of the Federal Elementary School in the incarceration camp.
        - Zenshin [characters] [Move Forward], no.3, 5-8. Crystal City. Monthly., March 1945; May-August 1945; (5 issues) (Box 333)
          A literary magazine published by the Zenshin-sha from January to August 1945 in the Crystal City detention facility.
    - Senji Tenjsho [characters] [Temporary Detention Center] Publications
      - The Central Utah Relocation Center, Topaz, Utah. (Box 334-335)
        - Adult Education Program. Topaz., 1943; (Mimeographed) (Box 335)
          A report prepared in May 1943 on the classes and programs offered by the Adult Education Program, Central Utah Relocation Center.
        - Co-op News. Topaz. Semi-weekly., December 1943-May 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 334)
          vol.2, no.15 (December 2, 1943)
          vol.3, no.5 (January 21, 1944)
          vol.3, no.12-13 (February 15 & 18, 1944)
          vol.3, no.15 (February 25, 1944)
          vol.5, no.17 (September 1, 1944)
          vol.6, no.1 (October 1, 1944)
          vol.6, no.6 (October 20, 1944)
          vol.6, no.9 (October 31, 1944)
          vol.6, no.20 (December 7, 194)
          vol.6, no.23 (December 19, 1944)
          vol.6, no.25-26 (December 27 & 29, 1944)
          vol.7, no.1-3 (January 5-12, 1945)
          vol.7, no.13 (February 16, 1945)
          vol.8, no.11 (May 18, 1945)
        - Pop [characters] [Poppies]. Topaz., October & December 1944; January-June 1945; and August 1945 (Box 335)
          A publication by the Pop no Kai [characters] [Poppy Haiku Club] in the Central Utah Relocation Center.
        - Pop no Kai [Poppy Haiku Club]. Pop Kush [characters] [Poppies: A collection of Haiku]. Topaz: Pop-sha., 1945; (Mimeographed, 49 pp.) (Box 335)
        - Tenj Jih [characters] [Relocation News]. Topaz. Irregular., June 2, 1945; June 13, 1945; July 11-August 1, 1945; August 22-September, 1945; September 21-28, 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 334)
          no.3-4 (June 2, 1945; June 13, 1945)
          no.8-11 (July 11-August 1, 1945)
          no.14-19 (August 22-September, 1945)
          no.21-23 (September 21-28, 1945)
        - Topaz High School. '43 Ramblings. Topaz. An annual., 1943 (Box 335)
        - Topzu Jih [characters] [Topaz Times News Daily]. Topaz. Irregular publication., October 1942-August 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 334)
          Volume 1, no.1 (October 29, 1942)-Volume 12, no.5 (August 3, 1945); and August 15 and 31 issues.
        - Topzu Shhi Kumiai [characters] [Topaz Co-op]. Topzu Shhi Kumiai Nishnen Kinen Shi [characters] [Two Years of the Topaz Co-op: Commemorative Publication]. Topaz,., 1944; (Mimeographed, 146 pp.) (Box 335)
      - The Colorado River Relocation Center, Poston, Arizona (Box 342-343)
        - Co-op Bulletin. No. 2. Poston., February 9, 1943; September 29, 1943; September 29, 1943; (2 items) (Box 342)
          Also, no.6, Kumiai Hkoku Yomimono Tokushg [characters] [Special Issue: report and essays], September 29, 1943.
        - Kigy Kumiai Nysu [characters] [Co-op Bulletin], no.6. Poston., November 1943; (Mimeographed) (Box 342)
        - Mohabe [characters] [Mojave]. Poston., June 1943-September 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 343)
          A monthly literary magazine.
          no.4 (June 1943)
          no.8 (October 1943)
          no.10 (December 1943)
          no.23-16 (March-June 1944)
          no.18 (August 194)
          no.20-22 (October-December 1944)
          no.24-31 (February-September 1945)
        - Poston High School. Post-Ano. Poston. An annual., 1944 (Box 342)
        - Posuton Bungei [characters] [Poston Poetry]. Poston. Monthly (?)., March 1943 and September 1945; (Mimeographed, 2 items) (Box 342)
          Published by the Posuton Bungei Kykai [characters] [Poston Poetry Club].
        - Family Welfare Orientation Program., 1944 (Box 798, Folder 9)
        - Poston Poetry Club. (Box 801, Folder 1-4)
          Twelve books of poetry and a high school yearbook.
      - Gila Relocation Center, Rivers, Arizona. (Box 335)
        - Desert Sentinel. Rivers. Biweekly., November 1942-January 1944; (Mimeographed) (Box 335)
          vol.1, no.4-5 (November 30 & December 24, 1942)
          vol.1, no.15 (June 21, 1943)
          vol.2, no.2 (October 8, 1943)
          October 22, 1943
          November 5, 1943
          December 19, 1943
          January 14, 1944
          January 24, 1944
        - Downing, Ferne, ed. Cactus Blossoms. Pasadena., 1945; (Mimeographed, 22 pp.) (Box 335)
          Poems written by students of the Butte High School, Rivers, Arizona.
        - Gila Co-op News. Rivers. Weekly., June 17-July 3, 1943; July 20-August 10, 1943; August 24, 1943; (Mimeographed) (Box 335)
          vol.1, no.1-3 (June 17-July 3, 1943)
          vol.1, no.5-8 (July 20-August 10, 1943)
          vol.1, no.10 (August 24, 1943)
        - Gila News Courier. Rivers. Tri-weekly., September 1942-September 1943; (Mimeographed) (Box 335)
          vol.1, no.1-2 (September 12 & 16, 1942)
          vol.1, no.8-9 (October 7 & 10, 1942)
          vol.2, no.4 (January 2, 1943)
          vol.4, no.3-5 (February 11-March 27, 1943)
          vol.4, no.74 (June 22, 1943)
          vol.4, no.76 (June 26, 1943)
          vol.3, no.4 (August 31, 1943)
          vol.3, no.9 (September 4, 1943)
          vol.3, no.13 (September 21, 1943)
        - Hi School News. Volume 1, no.3. Rivers., November 2, 1942; (Mimeographed) (Box 335)
        - Hira Jih [characters] [Gila News Courier], no.1-135. Rivers. Tri-weekly., October 7, 1942-September 11, 1943; (Mimeographed) (Box 335)
      - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado. (Box 336-338)
        - Amache High School. Onlooker. Amache. Annuals., 1944 & 1945; (2 items) (Box 338)
        - Granada Pioneer. Volume 1, no.1-Volume 3, no.91. Incomplete set. Amache. Tri-weekly., October 28, 1942; September 15, 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 337)
        - [Guranada Ginsha [characters]]. Guranada Ginsha Haiku-sh [characters] [Anthology of haiku, Granada Ginsha]., (Mimeographed, 106 pp.) (Box 338)
          A publication to commemorate the closing of the Granada Relocation Center.
        - Guranada Jih [characters] [Granada Times], no.5. Amache. Weekly., October 28, 1942; (Mimeographed) (Box 337)
          It continued publication under the title, the Paionia [Pioneer].
        - Paionia [characters] [Pioneer]. Incomplete set. Amache. Tri-weekly., October 30, 1942-September 1, 1944; (Mimeographed) (Box 336-337)
          no.6-vol.3, no.65 (October 30, 1942-September 1, 1944)
          Also, special editions (September 5 & 20, 1945).
        - YUGI Sangaku [characters], ed. Beiju [characters] [Eighty-eighth birthday celebration]. Amache., 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 338)
          A collection of haiku [characters], senry [characters], tanka [characters], and kanshi [characters], composed by friends in honor of NOBE Riichir who became 88 years old.
      - Heart Mountain Relocation Center, Wyoming. (Box 338)
        - Coordinator's Bulletin. Heart Mountain. Semi-weekly., n.d.; January 10-31, 1945; February 9-May 23, 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 338)
          no.3-4 (n.d.)
          no.6-11 (January 10-31, 1945)
          no.13-20 (February 9-May 23, 1945)
        - Hto Maunten Bungei [characters] [Heart Mountain Essay and Poetry Booklet]. Heart Mountain. Monthly., December 1943; March 1944; July 1944; and September 1944; (4 issues) (Box 338)
        - Htosan Senchineru-sha [characters]. Htosan Jimmeiroku [characters] [Roster of incarcerees in the Heart Mountain Relocation Center]. Heart Mountain., 1945; (Mimeographed, 74 pp.) (Box 338)
        - Heart Mountain Sentinel. Incomplete set. Heart Mountain. Weekly., January 1, 1943-May 26, 1945; December 18-19, 1944; October 23, 1945 (Box 338)
          Volume 2, no.1- Volume 4, no.22 (January 1, 1943-May 26, 1945)
          Supplement no.260-261 (December 18-19, 1944)
          Supplement no.359 (October 23, 1945)
        - TSUNEISHI Shisei [characters], tr. Zoku Yakushi Sh [characters] [English poems translated into Japanese]. Heart Mountain., 1945; (Mimeographed, 84 pp.) (Box 338)
      - Jerome Relocation Center, Denson, Arkansas. (Box 339)
        - Communique. Nos. 1-27, 29-41. Denson. Tri-weekly., October 23, 1942-January 15, 1943; January 19-February 26, 1943; (Mimeographed) (Box 339)
        - Denson Jih [characters] [Denson Jiho]. Denson. Tri-weekly., December 8, 1942-January 15, 1943; January 22-February 26, 1943; March 12, 1943; March 19, 1943; (Mimeographed) (Box 339)
          no.1-12 (December 8, 1942-January 15, 1943)
          no.14-24 (January 22-February 26, 1943)
          no.28 (March 12, 1943)
          no.30 (March 19, 1943)
        - Denson Tribune. Volume 1, no.4, 6. Denson. Tri-weekly., March 12, 1943; March 9, 1943; (Mimeographed) (Box 339)
      - Manzanar Relocation Center, California. (Box 339)
        - Manzanar Free Press. Scattered issues. Manzanar. Tri-weekly., April 11, 1942; July 22, 1942; (Mimeographed) (Box 339)
          vol.1, no.1 (April 11, 1942)
          vol.2, no.1 (July 22, 1942)
        - Manzanar High School. Our World. Manzanar. An Annual., 1943/1944 (Box 339)
        - Manzana Jiy Shimbun [characters] [Manzanar Free Press]. Volume 1, no.25, 30-35. Manzanar. Tri-weekly., June 18, 1942; June 30-July 11, 1942; (Mimeographed) (Box 339)
        - "Community Welfare Section" by Margaret D'Ille, Head Counselor., 1945 December 31 (Box 302)
        - Manzanar Whirlwind., 1945 March, June (Box 798, Folder unknown container)
      - Minidoka Relocation Center, Hunt, Idaho. (Box 339)
        - Hunt High School. Memoirs. Hunt. An annual., 1943 (Box 339)
        - The Minidoka Irrigator. Volume 3, no.2-6, 11-20. Hunt. Weekly., March 6-April 3, 1943; May 8-July 10, 1943; (Mimeographed) (Box 339)
        - Hunt Hi-Lites and Hunt High School U-Namet and other Minidoka materials., 1942-1944 (Box 798, Folder 10, 12, 13)
        - Stafford Press., 1943 (Box 798, Folder 11)
        - Teacher Training manual., 1943 July (Box 798, Folder 15)
          Also includes "Poston: The Characteristics of the Project Population - a handbook of general statistics."
        - Report of the Welfare Section by War Relocation Authority., 1945 (Box 798, Folder 16)
      - Rohwer Relocation Center, McGhee, Arkansas. (Box 340-342)
        - [KAYAMOTO Kinsh [characters], comp.]. Shish [characters] [Collection of verses]. McGhee., 1945; (Mimeographed, 157 pp.) (Box 342)
        - Red Cross Rohwer Relocation Center Unit. Rohwer Relocation Center, commemorating R.R.C. service, 1943-1945. McGhee., (Mimeographed, 17 pp.) (Box 342)
        - Rohwer Outpost. Volume 1, no.1- Volume 7, no.37. McGhee. Semi-weekly., October 24, 1942-July 21, 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 341-342)
        - Rohwer Outpost. The Pen. McGhee., 1943; (Mimeographed, 82. pp.) (Box 342)
          A booklet which highlights the first year of life in the Rohwer Relocation Center.
        - Rohwer Outpost. Lil Dan'l. McGhee., 1943; (Mimeographed, 28 pp.) (Box 342)
          Lil Dan'l is a cartoon character that appeared in the Rohwer Outpost.
        - Rohwer Relocator. Volume 1, no.1, 4-20, 22-28. McGhee. Irregular., May 5, 1945; June 16-September 21, 1945; September 28-November 9, 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 342)
        - Rwa Jih [characters] [Rohwer News]. Incomplete set.. McGhee. Tri-weekly., December 1942-January 6, 1943; January 13, 1943-November 14, 1945; (Mimeographed) (Box 340)
          vol.1, no.1-4 (December 1942-January 6, 1943)
          vol.2, no.4-Volume 7, no.37 (January 13, 1943-November 14, 1945)
        - Rwa Jih. Rwa no Ichinen [characters] [One-year at Rohwer]. McGhee. An information booklet., 1943; (Mimeographed, 66 pp.) (Box 342)
      - Samples of shugeihin [characters] [handicraft] made by the incarcerees in various incarceration camps.
        - The Tule Lake Relocation Center, Newell, California. (Box 346)
        - Other centers (unidentified). (Box 347)
    - War Relocation Authority publications and other publications, 1943-1945 (Box 798, Folder 3)
    - Manual of Evacuee Transfer Operations and War Relocation Authority memoranda., 1943 (Box 798, Folder 4-6)
    - Publications on race and forced removal. (Box 798, Folder 14, 17)
    - Diary and meeting minutes at Poston. (Box 799)
      Includes a typed diary, Community Council minutes, Colorado River Relocation Advisory Board minutes, Manpower Commission minutes, local council minutes, War Relocation Authority Colorado River War Relocation Project circular letters, Handbook of Statistics, Index-Digest of Opinions issued by the Office of the Solicitor, and quarterly and semiannual reports.
    - Diaries, reports, and censuses. (Box 801, Folder 5-13)
      Includes Jerome Relocation Center education report, Gambling at Poston report, Granada census roster, Ben Iijima's diary, Doris Hayashi's diary, and Poston census.
    - Tule Lake Manual of Evacuee Transfer Operations. (Box 796)
    - War Relocation Authority manual, Information Digest, Weekly Press Review, Community Analysis Reports, and administrative notices. (Box 802)
      Also includes Mr. Maurice Lipian's file of War Relocation Authority reports and administrative notices. War Relocation Authority documents include "Security of Resettlers" and "When You Leave the Relocation Center."
    - Map of Evacuee Reception Center Tanforan Race Track., 1942 May 9 (Box 865)
  - Publication of the War Relocation Authority (Box 344, 735-739, 797, 800)
    Materials include Administrative Handbook by Richard Lee Newlon (Part 1-Part 3), Administrative Manual (Part 1-2), English and Japanese language newspaper, administrative documents regarding incarceration camp and war relocation, map of Post-War Re-distribution of American - Japanese (February, 1946), record of council meetings by JACL, book Case for the Nisei, books and documents about Japanese Americans in WW2, and a series of War Relocation Authority publications by United States of the Interior.
- Published Materials
  (not included in previous categories)
  - Books and other Publications, 4.5 linear ft.
    - Booklets and Pamphlets Published by the Japanese in the United States
      - AKAHORI Masaru [characters], ed. Kika Shiken no Tora no Maki: Shiminken Nij-go-kamoku [characters] [Twenty-five lessons in citizenship]. Los Angeles: Town Crier (2nd edition)., 1950 and 1952; (44 p., 2 items) (Box 350)
      - AKAHORI Masaru. Koji KAGAWA Toyohiko [characters] [Orphans All: Toyohiko Kagawa]. Los Angeles: Taunkuraiy-sha, 1947., (44pp., 1 item) (Box 350)
        The Japanese translation and the original English text on KAGAWA Toyohiko in Ralph E. Downie, Orphans All (Seattle, 1936).
      - AKAHORI Masaru. Nanka Nihonjin Yaky-shi [characters] [History of Japanese baseball in Southern California]. Los Angeles: Town Crier., n.d.; (38 pp., 1 item (Box 230)
        A pictorial history.
      - Nichibei Shimbun-sha [characters] [The Japanese American News]. Zai-Bei Nihonjin Jimmei Jiten [characters] [Japanese Who's Who in America]. San Francisco: Nichibei Shimbun-sha., 1922; (742pp., 1 volume) (Box 352)
      - fu Nipp-sha [characters] [The Sacramento Daily News]. Sakuramento Heigen Nihonjin Taisei Ichiran [characters] [The Sacramento Valley: An overview of the Japanese residents]. Sacramento., 1909; 1919; (2 items) (Box 353)
        no.2 (1909), and No. 4 (1919)
        Annuals published by the fu Nipp-sha. The 1909 annual contains valuable statistical data on the Japanese residing in Sacramento and its vicinities, and a directory of the residents.
      - Rakki Jih-sha [characters] [The Rocky Mountain Times]. Sanchbu to Nihonjin [characters] [The Rocky Mountain region and the Japanese]. Salt Lake City: Rakki Jih-sha., 1925; (1 item, 609 pp.) (Box 354)
        A general history of the Japanese in the states of Idaho, Nevada, Utah, and Wyoming, compiled by the Rakki Jih- sha. It contains a Who's Who of over 6,000 individuals.
      - Shin Sekai Asahi Shimbun-sha [characters] [The Shin Sekai Asahi Shimbun]. Dh Katei oyobi Dai-Nisei Dai-kinen-ch [characters] [Memorial book of Japanese families in U.S.A.]. San Francisco: Shin Sekai Asahi Shimbun-sha., 1939; (1 item, 56 pp.) (Box 353)
      - Shin Sekai Shimbun-sha [characters] [The Shin Sekai Shimbun]. Panama Taiheiy Bankoku Dai-hakurankai: Dai-ichi and Dai-ni [characters] [Panama Pacific International Exposition: No. 1 and 2]. San Francisco: Shin Sekai Shimbun-sha. 1912 and 1914, 1912, 1914; (1 item) (Box 353, Box 869)
        No.1 in Box 353 Box and No.2 in Box 869.
        Two special publications in English and Japanese on the Panama Pacific International Exposition scheduled to open in 1915 to commemorate the opening of the Panama Canal.
      - Shin Sekai Shimbun-sha. Shwa Gurafu [characters] [The Showa Graph]. San Francisco: Shin Sekai Shimbun-sha., 1929; (1 item, 56 pp.) (Box 744)
        A photographic album to commemorate the coronation of the Shwa Emperor.
      - Shgy Jih-sha [characters] [The Commercial Times]. Hawaii Zairymin Gosokui Tairei Hshuku Kinen-ch [characters] [Commemorative publication to celebrate the coronation of the Shwa Emperor by the Japanese residents in Hawaii]. Honolulu: Shgy Jih-sha., 1928; (92 pp.) (Box 354)
      - SUZUKI Rokuhiko [characters], SAKUMA Tsunematsu [characters], SHIOMI Shun [characters], and FUYUMURO Shigeharu [characters]. Intmaunten Dh Hattatsu Shi [characters] [The development of the Intermountain Japanese colonies]. Denver: Demb Shimp-sha., 1910; (1 book, 629 pp.) (Box 354)
        The earliest history of the Japanese in the Rocky Mountain area, written by four different authors and published by the Demb Shimp-sha [characters]. In includes many valuable biographical sketches of Issei residents, as well as advertisements of Japanese labor contractors.
      - Takoma Shh-sha [characters] [The Tacoma Weekly]. Takoma-shi oyobi Chih Nihonjin Shi [characters] [History of the Japanese in Tacoma and Vicinity]. Tacoma: Takoma Shh-sha., 1941; (265 pp.) (Box 354)
      - Taunkuraiy-sha [characters] [The Town Crier]. Nihonkoku Kemp [characters] [Constitution of Japan]. Los Angeles: Taunkuraiy-sha., 1947; (1 item, 28 and 31pp., mimeographed) (Box 350)
      - Taunkuraiy Shimbun-sha [characters] [The Town Crier]. Kodakara [characters] [Children]. Los Angeles: Taunkuraiy Shimbun-sha., 1956; (24pp., 1 item) (Box 350)
        A booklet devoted to a Mother's Day program.
      - Taunkuraiy Shimbun-sha. Nanka Nikkeijin Eigy Annai [characters] [S. C. Japanese Guide]. Los Angeles: Taunkuraiy Shimbun-sha., 1963; (76pp., 1 item) (Box 350)
      - Town Crier. L. A. Japanese Telephone Directory. Los Angeles: Town Crier., 1946; (1 item, 22 pp.) (Box 350)
      - Books and booklets. (Box 362-363,370)
        regarding immigration, the Japanese in America, Nisei Mondai [the Second Generation problem], United States-Japan relations, and related topics.
        - Anju, Shhachi. Racial and National Exclusiveness. Berkeley (?)., 1919 (?); (1 item, 58pp. A booklet) (Box 362)
        - Beikoku Kakumei-sha [characters]. Kokka-ron [characters] [The State: Its Historic Role]. San Francisco: Beikoku Kakumei-sha., 1911; (1 item, 119 pp.) (Box 362)
          A Japanese translation of a political pamphlet written by Peter Kropotkin. Published by a small group of Japanese anarchists in the San Francisco Bay Area.
        - KIYAMA Yoshitaka [characters]. Manga Yonin Shosei [characters] [Cartoons of four students]. Oakland: Inhaku Dshi Kai., 1931; (1 book, 111 pp.) (Box 362)
          Covers such topics as being a school boy, working as a farmhand, drinking and gambling, the Great Earthquake of 1906, and picture-brides.
        - NIISATO Kan'ichi [characters]. Zaibei no Nihon Minzoku Go-hyaku-nen no Taikei [characters] [A 500-year plan for the Japanese in America]. Tokyo: Shimp-sha., 1940; (1 item, 97 pp.) (Box 370)
        - OKUMURA Takie [characters]. Hai-Nichi Yob Keihatsu Und [characters] [Educational campaign to prevent exclusion]. [Honolulu:] Privately printed., 1922 (?); (1 item, 60 pp.) (Box 363)
          The author advocates the Issei's assimilation into the American society, and encourages them to raise their children as American citizens.
        - OKUMURA Takie. Hawai ni okeru Nichi-Bei Mondai Kaiketsu Und [characters] [Campaign to solve the Japanese American problem in Hawaii]. 3rd edition. Honolulu: Privately printed., 1928; (1 item, 111 pp.) (Box 362)
          An expanded version is published in 1933.
        - Panama Pacific International Exposition (Box 869)
          Two booklet on Panama Pacific
        - SHIMADA Gunkichi [characters]. Shishiboe [characters] [A lion's roar]. Honolulu: Privately printed., 1916; (1 item, 176 pp.) (Box 362)
          A collection of miscellaneous essays with one chapter on the Japanese exclusion movement in America, pp. 95-107.
        - TSUNODA Rysaku [characters]. Shosai, Gakk, Shakai [characters] [Study, School, and Society]. Honolulu: Hawai Benri-sha., 1917; (1 book, 295 pp.) (Box 362)
          The author who later became Professor at Columbia University, was then a teacher associated with the Hompa Hongwanji Mission in Hawaii. In Japanese.
    - Poetry, 1.5 linear ft.